A Guide to the Charles L. Hoagland papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA167
Rockefeller Archive Center
Charles L. Hoagland papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Hoagland, Charles L.
FA167
1 Cubic Feet Actual extent is unknown.
2½" letter GL 5/86
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Lee Hoagland, 1907-1946. At RIMR 1937-1938, 1939-1946.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 H65
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Hoagland, Charles L.
- Biographical material (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical information includes appointments at RIMR and salary thru 1942, 1942 January
  - Biographical information. Prepared at Mr. Flinn's, Business Manager, request for Dr. Gasser, 1946 July 3
  - Same as July 31 but includes date of death, Aug 2, 1946, circa 1946 August 2
  - Obituary and biographical information prepared at time of Dr. Hoagland's death, circa 1946 August 2
  - Henry Allen Moe, Secretary, The Century Association/ T. M. Rivers? requesting assistance in preparing a memorial for Dr. Hoagland, circa 1946 August 12
  - Rivers/Henry Allen Moe, re Dr. Hoagland biographical and professional information w/enclosure: ca 1946 Aug 2, obituary prepared at time of Dr. Hoagland's death, 1946 August 19
  - Thomas M. Rivers, "Charles Lee Hoagland 1907-1946." (To be read before the meeting of the Interurban Clinical Club, Cleveland, Ohio on Dec 5 or 6, 1947), 1947 October 28; 3 pp, carbon copy
- Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1934-1946, 5 pp
  - In press. Incomplete, 1934-1940; 3 pp
- Correspondence, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rivers, T. M. /Gasser, H. S. re Hoagland application for position on Dr. Avery's service in the RIMR Hospital, w/Enclosures, 1937 September 2
    - Charles Lee Hoagland's application for appointment to RIMR, 1937 September 28
    - Letters of recommendation for Hoagland, 2 letters
      - Ralph Muckenfuss/Rivers, 1937 September
      - David Barr/Rivers, 1937 September 1
  - Gasser, H. S. /Rivers, T. M. re Hoagland's appointment as resident physician at RIMR Hospital beginning Oct 1, 1937, 1937 September 2
  - Rivers/Gasser re letter to Dr. Barr re Hoagland, 1939 March 3
  - Rivers/Gasser re Hoagland appointment as Resident in Hospital and Associate Physician, beginning July 1, 1939 w/H. S. Gasser acknowledgment, Apr 1, 1939, 1939 March 3
  - Edric B. Smith/Hoagland re Article VIII of the By-Laws of the Corporation enclosure, 1939 April 1
  - Federal Housing Administration, Kansas City, Mo/RI. Request for information re Hoagland applying for mutual mortgage insurance and E. B. Smith reply, Apr 22, 1940, 1940 April 1
  - B. Lupinek/E. B. Smith, re alterations to Rooms 302 to 307, Central Bldg (Founder's) for Dr. Hoagland, 1941 April
  - Brown, Wheelock, Harris, Stevens, Inc. / E. B. Smith. Request for references on Dr. Hoagland as a proposed tenant w/E. B. Smith reply, Apr 10, 1941, 1941 April 1
  - RI Business Manager/Hoagland re Helena Gilder, 1942 June 3
  - Estimate of Dr. Hoagland's Laboratory Rooms 301-305 Central Building, undated
  - Telephone message from Dr. Hoagland re discharge from Naval Reserve as of Dec 31, 1942, 1943 January 1
  - Hoagland's Classification Notice (1-C) from Local Board, Selective Service, 1944 December 2
  - re Hoagland's appointment as "Civilian Consultant in the Medical Consultants' Division of the Surgeon General's Office -..". Handwritten and typewritten notes, 1944 December 20
  - Commanding General, Military District of Washington/RIMR inquiry re Hoagland's employment with 1945 Jan 31 reply on reverse side, 1945 January 2
  - Business Manager, RIMR/Hoagland re Daniel H. Labby, Henry G. Kunkel and Max Bovarnick, 1945 April 2
  - Secretary, Board of Scientific Directors, RIMR/Hoagland re Hoagland appointment as an editor for JEM, 1946 June 14
  - Business Manager/Hoagland, re laboratory budget in Hospital, July 1, 1946-June 30, 1947, 1946 June 2
  - Waldo R. Flinn/H. S. Gasser, re Hoagland's serious condition in RI Hospital, 1946 July 2
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - probably 1938, 1 5 × 7
  - undated, 8 × 10 multiple copies
    Scope and Contents note
    [Used in 1946 Aug newspaper obituaries for Dr. Hoagland].
- Obituary material (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes, handwritten and typed, prior to and after Dr. Hoagland's death re funeral arrangements, lists of publications for obituary notices, 1946 July 31-August
  - E. B. Smith/various publications re Hoagland w/Encls: Biographical sketch and photo to: JAMA, Science Service, Science Press, 1946 August
  - E. B. Smith telegrams re Hoagland's death and services in Carthage, Mo. to: John D. Rockefeller Jr., O. T. Avery, James B. Conant, Ross G. Harrison, Frank L. Horsfall, Warfield T. Longcope, Homer F. Swift, George Whipple w/reply by telegram, 2 Aug 1946 from John D. Rockefeller Jr., 1946 August
  - Many handwritten notes re funeral arrangements, place and date of funeral services and persons to be notified [by E. B. Smith?], 1946 August
  - Obituaries re Charles L. Hoagland. Newspaper clippings
    - New York World-Telegram, "Dr. C. L. Hoagland Dies at Age of 39", 1946 August
    - New York Sun, "Dr. Hoagland is Dead at 39", 1946 August
    - New York Times, "Dr. Hoagland Dies: Rockefeller Aide". and "Hoagland, Charles Lee", 1946 August 3
    - New York Herald Tribune, "Dr. Charles L. Hoagland Dies; On Rockefeller Institute Staff", 1946 August
  - Bus. Mgr/John D. Rockefeller Jr. re telegram, flowers, funeral arrangements, Dr. Hoagland's foster parents, Mr. and Mrs. McCawley, 1946 August
  - Bus Mgr/H. S. Gasser re obituary notice in Sunday, Times and Herald Tribune, 1946 August
  - James A. Moffett (Patient) /RIMR re Hoagland, 1946 August
  - Handwritten letters addressed to T. M. Rivers re Hoagland from
    - Warfield T. Longcope, 1946 August
    - Julius Neuberger, 1946 August
    - N. H. Martin, 1946 August
    - Dan Labby and John D. Rockefeller Jr. w/T. M. Rivers replies, 6 and 8 Aug 1946, 1946 August
  - H. Gilder/T. M. Rivers re Hoagland, 1946 August 1
  - Francis Binkley/T. M. Rivers re Hoagland w/T. M. Rivers replies of Aug 16 and 19, 1946 August 1
  - T.M. Rivers, "Charles Lee Hoagland 1907-1946." for inclusion in the Minutes of the Rockefeller Institute Board. Signed E.H., 1947 January; 5 pp carbon copy, and duplicated copy pp 5-9
  - Sec'y, Board of Scientific Directors, RIMR/Mr. Alfred L. McCawley. Copy of memorial minute to the McCawleys, by T. M. Rivers adopted by RIMR, Bd of Sci Dirs, 18 Jan 1947, 1947 February 1
  - Memorial minute by T. M. Rivers to be read before the meeting of the Interurban Clinical Club, Cleveland, Ohio, Dec 5 or 6, 1947, 1947 October 2; 3 pp, typescript, carbon copy
- Obituary material. Extra copies of (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Biographical sketch of Charles L. Hoagland sent to various publications by E. B. Smith, Business Manager, RIMR, 1946 August
  - T. M. Rivers, "Charles Lee Hoagland 1907-1946" for inclusion in the Minutes of the RIMR Board of Scientific Directors at meeting held on Jan 18, 1947. Multiple copies, 1947 January 6
- Posthumous correspondence, 1947 1948 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Credit slip from Perkins Elmer Corp for 1 Flame Photometer - Model 18-#115 for $375.00
  - Return receipt of insured parcel signed by Mrs. A. L. McCawley. [Possibly items belonging to Dr. Hoagland sent to the McCawley's], 1947 February 20
  - Exchange re payment of royalties owed by Interscience Publishers to estate of Dr. Charles L. Hoagland to Mr. Alfred L. McCawley, 1948 September 23-1953 May